<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>FOAR705 Digital Humanities</title>
    <description>This unit explores cross-disciplinary approaches to research that fall under the rubric of ‘digital humanities’,  the aim of which is to use technological tools to solve domain problems. and present results in an accessible way.
</description>
    <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="MQ-FOAR705.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 15:38:07 +1000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 15:38:07 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quick Guide to Posting on the Blog via NeCTAR</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is just a quick guide of the steps I take to post on the blog using a NeCTAR virtual machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nectar-virtual-machine&quot;&gt;NeCTAR Virtual Machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nectar.org.au/&quot;&gt;https://nectar.org.au/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;em&gt;Cloud Login&lt;/em&gt; and login with university credentials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click &lt;em&gt;Instances&lt;/em&gt; in left tab and then select &lt;em&gt;Launch Instance&lt;/em&gt; on the right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give your instance a name, change flavour to m2.small&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose &lt;em&gt;NeCTAR Fedora 23 x86_64 (450.1 MB)&lt;/em&gt; for Image Name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click Access and Security tab and choose your key pair and select SSH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hit the &lt;em&gt;Launch&lt;/em&gt; button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now our instance will start up. Give it a moment to initialise/spawn. Once it is done, grab the IP address so we can login via SSH.
SSH Login via your preferred method - Linux terminal, PuTTY, MobaXTerm etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE - The user name for the fedora machine is &lt;em&gt;ec2-user&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For PuTTY we put &lt;em&gt;ec2-user@255.255.255.255&lt;/em&gt; in the Host Name box under Session, replacing the 255.255.255.255 with the IP address of our NeCTAR virtual machine. You also need to add your user key under Connection &amp;gt; SSH &amp;gt; Auth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cloning-the-github&quot;&gt;Cloning the GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already have github setup so lets clone it and work from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;sudo dnf install git
git clone https://github.com/MQ-FOAR705/MQ-FOAR705.github.io.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want to use the SSH method of cloning (rather than the https one I’m using here) that Brian discussed in class, assuming that you have setup your SSH keypair. I’ll leave this up to someone else to write a quick tutorial on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-jekyll&quot;&gt;Installing Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have the github cloned, lets navigate to that folder and install the jekyll github pages gem bundle. In the github I’ve already setup a Gemfile so we are all ready to go and install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;sudo dnf install ruby-devel redhat-rpm-config gcc zlib-devel nodejs
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;MQ-FOAR705.github.io
gem install bundler
bundle install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-a-post&quot;&gt;Writing a Post&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we write a post, we want to make sure we have the latest files from git, so we need to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt; from the MQ-FOAR705.github.io directory. This is a really important step so that we avoid any commit conflicts. Once git pull has been done, we can &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd _posts&lt;/code&gt; to get into the _posts directory to create a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just going to use nano for my text editor, but you might prefer something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo dnf install nano&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now lets make a post. The naming structure of the post is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-Your-Post-Name.markdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the post I’m going tp make for today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nano 2016-04-08-Quickguide.markdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the post we first need to add a YAML header which goes between three dashes at the top of the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;---
layout: post
title: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Quick Guide to Posting on the Blog via NeCTAR&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
description: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;This is just a quick guide of the steps I take to post on the blog using a NeCTAR virtual machine&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
author: Cooper B
categories: nectar jekyll blog github
---&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layout section tells it to use the post layout. The title is, well, the title of the blog post. The description part is the little blurb that shows on the front page under the title. The author will show up with the date of the post. Categories are like tags that the post is filed under.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’ve done that we can add some content underneath using markdown. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is a good markdown cheatsheet. The main style setup for headers in the blog is header 2 which you can signify by using a double hash &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;##&lt;/code&gt; before a line of text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;testing-out-our-changes&quot;&gt;Testing Out Our Changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can preview our changes with by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt; from the MQ-FOAR705.github.io folder&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually this provides a local web server on the loopback device a port 4000 - which we access by opening a web browser and navigating to &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/a&gt; - However, now we run into a problem where we cannot access the localhost loopback device because we are on a remote virtual machine. The simplest solution to this that I found was to use ngrok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First lets make sure we are in our home directory using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd ~&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~
sudo dnf install wget
wget https://bin.equinox.io/c/4VmDzA7iaHb/ngrok-stable-linux-amd64.zip
unzip ngrok-stable-linux-amd64.zip
chmod +x ngrok&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ngrok allows us to pass a localhost port to an ngrok webpage by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;./ngrok 4000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we want to run ngrok and jekyll serve side by side, so we need to run one as a background process which we can do by adding an ampersand &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; after the command. I’ve written a little bash script in the MQ-FOAR705.github.io folder that will automate this process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/MQ-FOAR705.github.io
./servejekyll.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you run this script you should get something along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;Tunnel Status                 online
Version                       2.0.25/2.0.25
Region                        United States &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;us&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
Web Interface                 http://127.0.0.1:4040
Forwarding                    http://27326b6e.ngrok.io -&amp;gt; localhost:4000
Forwarding                    https://27326b6e.ngrok.io -&amp;gt; localhost:4000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grab the forwarding address, which in this case is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://27326b6e.ngrok.io&lt;/code&gt; - though this will change whenever you run it. Now you can put this in your webbrowser and you should be able to see everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-a-commit&quot;&gt;Making a Commit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are happy with the changes, hit Ctrl+C to close the ngrok command. As we already ran the jekyll serve command alongside ngrok by running the script, then we don’t need to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll build&lt;/code&gt; as it will have already done it for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;git add -A
git commit -a -m &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;my awesome changes&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! Hopefully you have just pushed your first post to the blog and haven’t completely burnt the place down! Don’t worry if you have messed something up - the great thing about github is that it saves all the revisions to the code, so anything drastic that happens we can just rollback to a previous working commit and go from there. But hopefully we wont need to do that :D&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/nectar/jekyll/blog/github/2016/04/08/quickguide.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">MQ-FOAR705.github.io/nectar/jekyll/blog/github/2016/04/08/quickguide.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>nectar</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>github</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why do Digital Humanities Projects often use Open Source Software Tools?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/zUzImht.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Source Water&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Source: Niels Heidenreich&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Magic Cauldron&lt;/em&gt;, Raymond uses rational choice theory to demonstrate why a business might find greater value in preferring open – rather than closed – source software implementations. These arguments for free open source software (FOSS) are built from Raymond’s previous discussion in &lt;em&gt;The Cathedral and the Bazaar&lt;/em&gt; regarding how FOSS ideologies create an effective environment for software development. Many of the points raised by Raymond directly relate to why a researcher might prefer FOSS to solve domain problems in digital humanities projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key point Raymond raises regards constructive laziness: considering that results trump effort, beginning from a partial solution is nearly always preferable to starting from scratch. As FOSS projects are free (as in speech, &lt;em&gt;libre&lt;/em&gt;), they are readily available to be adapted and modified to any specific needs. Raymond observes that it is only through praxis that problems are truly understood: hence, it is likely that initial solutions will be inadequate and require modification or even complete rethinking. With proprietary software this means either being locked into a poor solution (because the code cannot be modified) or expending financial resources on new solutions.  Free (as in beer, &lt;em&gt;gratis&lt;/em&gt;) FOSS tools allow for rapid prototyping, thus rapid failures, and therefore rapidly better solutions without snowballing financial costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOSS can also be used as a ‘strategic weapon’ (Raymond 2000). Free (libre) code means that similar projects are not forced to implement individual solutions in parallel, but instead can improve, modify and adapt existing project code, thus contributing back to the project. A development base built across a wide community allows for cost sharing. This also provides risk spreading by ensuring that even if the original developers leave, other developers can fill the gaps, thus preventing users from being left with projects reliant on orphaned software. This contrasts sharply with proprietary software where users are reliant on the company considering the software valuable enough to continue development and support. Furthermore, the free (gratis) nature of FOSS allows it to act as a market loss leader, preventing corporate price fixing and monopolistic control over how solutions should be implemented.
For Raymond, FOSS is particularly valuable when projects require independent peer review for verifying correctness of design and implementation (something all academic research requires). Free (libre) code translates to transparent code.  The collaborative community aspects of FOSS combine with this transparency to increase accountability and replicability. Moreover, best practices arise more rapidly as other users see different approaches to problems, provide small suggestions and questions that lead to new ways of thinking, or see previously overlooked issues. Raymond (2000) summarises this effect as ‘many eyeballs tame complexity’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOSS is frequently criticised as having a free rider problem: why submit patches if doing so only benefits others? Firstly, as noted, academic research requires peer review: obfuscating methods only hinders this process. Moreover, beyond selecting appropriate approaches to research, it is rarely methods that make research valuable. Rather, it is how researchers analyse and interpret collected data so as to advance the existing knowledge in their field. Additionally, according to game theory, whilst intuitively it seems altruistic to submit code to FOSS projects, it is, in fact, optimally selfish. The cost has already been incurred in creating patches. By not submitting patches, the cost of maintaining patches for subsequent updates falls on the patch holder. Merging patches with source places that cost back onto the community of developers that maintain the project. Furthermore, submission of the patch fosters collaborative involvement amongst the community and therefore increases development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I have outlined just a few of the many benefits that FOSS provides to academic researchers. However, despite the significant benefits, this is not to suggest FOSS is some utopian catchall solution. As with all tools, it is important to justify selection against the available alternatives so as to make the best choice for the problem at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raymond, E.S. 2000, &lt;em&gt;The Cathedral and the Bazaar&lt;/em&gt;, http://www.catb.org/esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/digitalhumanities/dh/writing/raymond/esr/2016/04/08/Why-do-digital-humanities-use-FOSS.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">MQ-FOAR705.github.io/digitalhumanities/dh/writing/raymond/esr/2016/04/08/Why-do-digital-humanities-use-FOSS.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>digitalhumanities</category>
        
        <category>dh</category>
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
        <category>raymond</category>
        
        <category>esr</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>This is David demonstrating github commits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is David, from David’s Machine, talking to you over the series of pipes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is italic&lt;/em&gt; and the asterisk is a symbol of the markdown markup language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;this is underlined&lt;/em&gt; and the underscore is a symbol of the markdown markup language.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/techdemo/2016/04/08/Hello-From-David.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">MQ-FOAR705.github.io/techdemo/2016/04/08/Hello-From-David.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>techDemo</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://timjames.me/img/jekyll/feature.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;github jekyll image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;source: http://timjames.me/img/jekyll/feature.jpg&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first foray into the world of Jekyll so I will be documenting my progress here. It seems scary at first, but as you get into it it really isn’t as terrifying as it seems, I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-jekyll-on-fedora&quot;&gt;Installing Jekyll on Fedora&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://linuxsuperuser.com/install-jekyll-on-fedora-23/&quot;&gt;http://linuxsuperuser.com/install-jekyll-on-fedora-23/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;sudo dnf install ruby-devel
sudo dnf install redhat-rpm-config
gem install jekyll&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing Jekyll on Fedora was a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/quickstart/&quot;&gt;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/quickstart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;jekyll new nameofblog
cd nameofblog
jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the jekyll server is running, we can fire up our web browser and navigate to: &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failing-early-failing-often-lets-get-some-content&quot;&gt;Failing Early, Failing Often: Lets get some content.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll can feel a little intimidating at first. No point trying to read mountains of documentation on all the various technical features, I’m just going to jump in. Best practice for learning FOSS is to fail early/often to learn better solutions and approaches: theory is no substitute for praxis. Luckily, we have the internet and surely others have failed before us, so lets employ our constructive laziness!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lmgtfy.com/?q=jekyll+tutorial&quot;&gt;http://lmgtfy.com/?q=jekyll+tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay lets go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;customising-appearance&quot;&gt;Customising Appearance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I go and push my blog to a github page, I’m going to have a go at editing things locally and viewing them on the localhost jekyll server.
We can change the settings of our landing page in the _config.yml file. I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sublimetext.com/3&quot;&gt;sublimetext3&lt;/a&gt; for my text editor as multiple cursors and extensive plugin support cannot be beaten in my eyes (plus its cross platform compatible which is super important for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you open up the _config.yml you will notice that it has the same text as the localhost landing page. Editing it seems pretty straightforward to me. Just edit the text after the colon for the particular section. Let’s give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I edited the part after title, but it didn’t seem like my page was updating when I hit refresh on my browser for the localhost:4000 page. So I quit the jekyll server from terminal by hitting Ctrl+C and then re ran it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I can see my changes. 
Not really keen on having my email shared on my blog, so I deleted that line. Updated my description. Going well so far. Now that I’ve got some basic content on my page, I’m going to look at changing the style sheet for the blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sass-scss-style-sheets&quot;&gt;SASS: SCSS Style Sheets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Style Sheet is in my-jekyll-folder/css/main.scss
First up I’m going to change the font family from Helevetica Neue to Source Sans Pro which is a fantastic freely available grotesque sans serif font developed by Paul D Hunt for Adobe. It is distributed under the SIL Open Font license. So in the spirit of FOSS, this is my font!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other good sans-serif free fonts are OpenSans, Liberation Sans, Droid Sans, Roboto, Bebas Neue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty easy so far.
I’ve noticed that other changes outside of _config.yml auto update, so no need to restart the server when making changes here. Just hit refresh
The templates for the pages and posts are in my-jekyll-folder/_layouts and you can edit the header and foot html in my-jekyll-folder/_includes
_sass/_layout.scss&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main style changes occur in my-jekyll-folder/_sass/_layout.scss&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I fire up sublimetext3 and open the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not super familiar with SASS style sheets, but looks fairly straight forward. First thing I want to do is change my Post Title style for my posts. So I scroll down to the Posts section in my text editor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot; data-lang=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.post-title&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;800&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;italic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;42px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#777&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;letter-spacing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;-1px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;line-height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;media-query($on-laptop)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;36px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah-Ha! .post-title seems to be what I’m looking for! A quick change of the font size and refresh in the browser confirms this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to change the weight of the font for post titles so I add font-weight to the section. From the main.scss file I know that our standard font weight is 400, but I decide I want a lighter standard weight so I change it to 200 and then I want the header to be Extra Bold / Heavy so I choose 800 for the post title weight. I also want to change the post title font colour to be a lighter gray colour so I add color: #777 which is short hand for #777777 which is the rgb hexadecimal colour code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W3schools has lots of info on CSS editing:   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3schools.com/css/css_font.asp&quot;&gt;http://www.w3schools.com/css/css_font.asp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uploading-to-github&quot;&gt;Uploading to Github&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve got the basic styles set up how I want and I started putting this content in the example post in the _posts folder, I’m going to have a go at putting this up on github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m following the instruction here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;https://pages.github.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also saw these instructions from git hub about using bundler so I followed them: &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-your-github-pages-site-locally-with-jekyll/&quot;&gt;https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-your-github-pages-site-locally-with-jekyll/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I used bundler I needed to install nodejs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;sudo dnf install nodejs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve got everything set up I go to github and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/new&quot;&gt;create a new repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to set the repository name as yourusername.github.io&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the repo is set up, open terminal and go to the jekyll page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git init
git add *
git commit -a -m &quot;first commit&quot;
git remote add origin https://github.com/user/repo.git
git push -u origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when we make changes commit the files and the push the commmits&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git commit -a -m &quot;commit message&quot;
git push origin --all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jekyll pages are at is at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mergeandvary.github.io/&quot;&gt;http://mergeandvary.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;
mergeandvary is my github page, just swap that part for your own username.
username.github.io&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-markdown&quot;&gt;Learning Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My initial blogging attempts were all done with a mix of markdown and html. Jekyll is great in that it lets you mix things up. However, for the sake of consistency I decided to learn a bit about markdown formatting and stick to one style as much as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a great &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet&quot;&gt;markdown cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/jekyll/update/2016/04/03/welcome-to-jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">MQ-FOAR705.github.io/jekyll/update/2016/04/03/welcome-to-jekyll.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Setting up Nectar Cloud with X forwarding over SSH</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://nectar.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/nectardirectorate-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nectar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government spent a ton of money ($4.94 million allocated in 2015) on National eResearch Collaboration Tools and Resources (NeCTAR) and we get two free machines through the university, so lets set one up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nectar.org.au/&quot;&gt;https://nectar.org.au/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-nectar&quot;&gt;Setting up NeCTAR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goto Cloud Login&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After login through Macquarie, go to Images in the left menu pane.
Find the NeCTAR Ubuntu 14.04 Image and choose “Launch Instance” from right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then give your instance a name. Choose your flavour which basically is just how powerful you want your VM to be. Larger sizes increase RAM, Disk Space, and Processing Power – however, they also use more of your NeCTAR alocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the right hand side you can see the details of your flavour and how much of your allocation that it will use. I’m going for the small, as tiny seemed a little too, well, tiny…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to add your SSH key in the Access &amp;amp; Security Tab! I thankfully have Petra’s blog post to follow, yet despite the warnings I was overly eager to set up the VM and missed this step. Had to delete it and restart, because I also think I can just dive in without following instructions… :p&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose your Key Pair and Check the SSH box&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After hitting the green Launch button, the instance will build in the Instances tab on the left (Surprise! Who would have thought.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launching-into-ssh&quot;&gt;Launching into SSH.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Instance is initialised, get the IP address from Instances tab
Open Terminal. (I’m using Linux for initial tests. I will switch to Windows once I get it working on Linux).
I saved my key file to ~/.ssh/Nectar_Key so I ran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;ssh -i ~/.ssh/Nectar_Key ubuntu@ip.address.of.instance&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I got this error!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;INSERT IMAGE HERE!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had to use chmod 600 to change my key’s permissions to only give me (file owner) read/write access (the 6 which is 2 + 4 i.e. read + write bits) and no one else in the file group or outside the file group (the two 0s).
Then I ran a simple apt-get update / apt-get dist-upgrade on the VM to make sure everything was up to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-on-to-the-fun-part-forwarding-x-over-ssh&quot;&gt;Now on to the fun part. Forwarding X over SSH&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the -X flag for ssh provides X forwarding e.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;ssh -i ~/.ssh/Nectar_Key ubuntu@ip.address -X&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I quickly noticed that because we are using a Server image of ubuntu, no X11 tools or GUI elements are installed. I installed them with the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;sudo apt-get install ubuntu-desktop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command needs to fetch about 559mb of archives and uses 2,128mb of space (2.0gb pretty much!). So this is where I’m glad that I chose the Small flavour rather than the Tiny one, as the extra 25gb of space goes a long way!
Looks like about 25min wait time on MQ network, so I’ll leave this running in my terminal and go do some other work in the meantime. See you soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m back…
Ubuntu desktop has installed. Now I exist my SSH session and relogin with X forwarding enabled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;ssh -i ~/.ssh/Nectar_Key ubuntu@ip.address -X&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that nautilus is the file browser in Ubuntu, so I type the command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nautilus&lt;/code&gt; and hit enter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now on to Windows!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-joy-sarcasm-of-windows&quot;&gt;The Joy &amp;lt;/sarcasm&amp;gt; of Windows.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PuTTY has the ability for X11 forwarding over SSH.
HOWEVER, as we’re not in Kansas (Linux) anymore, that means we also need an X server like Xming. 
As I’m not really that keen on setting up an X server in windows, I’m going to go another route which is using MobaXTerm. MobaXTerm is a terminal program for windows that has an X11 server built in and is free for personal use.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mobaxterm.mobatek.net/download.html&quot;&gt;http://mobaxterm.mobatek.net/download.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you open mobaXterm you get a home page like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMAGE FILE MISSING&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select Start local terminal
And then the commands are the same as before. I recommend saving your Nectar_Key pem file on the Desktop. Then you can use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;ssh -i Desktop/Nectar_Key ubuntu@ip.address -X
nautilus&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;terminal-tips&quot;&gt;Terminal Tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget you can use Ctrl+C as a terminal break command. Nautilus will be running in the terminal window so just switch back to the terminal and hit Ctrl+C to end the process if you need to. You can use an ampersand &amp;amp; at the end of a command to run it as a separate process thread if you still need to do work in the terminal window at the same time. e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nautilus &amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-final-note-reseting-nectar-vm&quot;&gt;A Final Note: Reseting NeCTAR VM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I noticed was that after I installed ubuntu-desktop. Apt-get was telling me that my system needed a restart. Not quite sure how I go about that. I’m going to try in the SSH terminal:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo shutdown -r now&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And see if my Nectar VM blows up! 
Basically the shutdown command tells the machine to, well, shutdown… The -r flag is for reboot and the now at the end tells it to do it now. Pretty self explanatory. 
After you run the command terminal / putty etc. will kick you out of the SSH session as the machine has gone offline. I’m going to try reconnecting now and see what happens.
And after I try reconnecting I get this scary message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMAGE MISSING&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering I just rebooted (and its probably related to that) and I’m not that worried about the integrity of my VM, I’m just going to  delete my key and start again:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ssh-keygen -R ip.address.of.vm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It finds my host key and removes it from my keychain. Then I just login again. Accept the new ECDSA fingerprint and we’re away!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/nectar/nectarcloud/nectarresearch/research/2016/04/03/setting-up-nectar-cloud.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">MQ-FOAR705.github.io/nectar/nectarcloud/nectarresearch/research/2016/04/03/setting-up-nectar-cloud.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>nectar</category>
        
        <category>nectarcloud</category>
        
        <category>nectarresearch</category>
        
        <category>research</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How the internet talks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well, the mostly young and mostly male users of Reddit, anyway.&lt;/em&gt;
(Olson &amp;amp; King 2015)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project examines the use of language on Reddit, with an aim to compare word trends across time. Olson and King (2015) parsed every comment on Reddit from late 2007 through August 2015. From this data, a tool was built which can plot graphs comparing the usage frequency of selected words over time. The tool also provides users the ability to share their generated graphs on Reddit or Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shear volume of data involved in a project such as this necessitates a digital medium. As of June 2015, Reddit had over 200 million users who have collectively posted more than 1.7 billion posts (Olson &amp;amp; King 2015). By automating the process of data collection, the authors are able to readily access data about word trends on the internet in a quantifiable way that is simply not possible with more traditional approaches to such research. However, despite collecting a large amount of data, potential analysis depth is very limited. Namely, the project lacks contextual data on the discursive space the words are used in. There is no data collected on how, where or when words are used, what they respond to, or how their connotative properties may change. That is, there is no way to analyse how the words interact - whether a “wtf” is used in playful surprise, disagreement or anger. Nonetheless, to analyse these elements would require a much greater degree of complexity in the project code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, the project’s simplicity is its greatest strength. The project mines a large amount of data in a fairly trivial manner, whilst providing access to that data in a simple and easily understood way. Further, because the tool allows users to search any combination of words, the data is not limited to the value structures inherent in the research design. The researchers have not nominated specific sets of words to be valued and counted – they have counted the whole of all sets. This allows future research projects to adapt the available data to their needs. For instance, I have used the tool to generate a graph comparing the usage of the terms “Troll”, “Trolling”, “Harassment” and “Bullying” (see link for graph). There is a significant spike to the term “troll” around 2011. This correlates with my observations of a significant mass-media moral panic surrounding this topic, particularly in regards to “RIP Trolling”, at this time. Also of note is a recent decline in the use of the terms “Troll” and “Trolling” alongside spikes in the “Harassment” term. This may indicate a discourse shift to a greater level of delineation between trolling and harassment behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That the authors note a predominantly male user-base aged under 35 years old highlights an area for potential improvement: namely, demographic breakdowns of word usage. This could be achieved, for instance, by collecting data on users’ profile information and the sub-Reddit they posted in, or by widening the data collection to include other websites with different demographic profiles. Nonetheless, increasing the dimensional space of the tool is likely to impact upon both simplicity and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olson, R &amp;amp; King, R 2015, ‘How the Internet talks* : *Well, the mostly young and mostly male users of Reddit, anyway. : reddit-ngram’, FiveThirtyEight, URL: https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/reddit-ngram/?keyword=troll.trolling.bullying.harassment&amp;amp;start=20071015&amp;amp;end=20150831&amp;amp;smoothing=10 &amp;lt;accessed 3 March 2016&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>MQ-FOAR705.github.io/writingprojects/dh/2016/03/03/how-the-internet-talks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">MQ-FOAR705.github.io/writingprojects/dh/2016/03/03/how-the-internet-talks.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>writingprojects</category>
        
        <category>dh</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
